All right, come join us.
It's time to get our afternoon set of sessions going here in the RISC-V pavilion for everyone
off, running around, grab your coffee, grab your friends, come join us.
So I'm Calista Redmond, CEO of RISC-V International, and I'm super excited to share with you a
little bit of the progress that we're seeing in our community, across industries, and importantly,
around the world.
So thanks so much for showing up.
Let me just start with a quick note on global standards.
You know, standards have underpinned so many of the amazing things, so many amazing innovations
that we have around the world.
You think about things like Wi-Fi and Bluetooth and the innovation that these have ushered
in.
That is so critical as each of us plays a part.
Each of us is a stakeholder in that overall technical economy, that we want what we build,
what our innovations are, to truly interoperate with one another.
RISC-V is a standard.
It's a standard instruction set architecture.
That means that we care about the interconnect between the software indicating what that
hardware needs to do.
And when it does that effect.
And effectively, it doesn't matter what the software is or what the underlying hardware is.
It's that interconnect.
It's that global standard that we are all very grateful for.
Because think of it this way.
The innovation that RISC-V has unleashed.
We now have more design houses on RISC-V than any other architecture in history.
If you look at the number of architectures in history, there are about 50.
I know that's surprising because you look at the landscape today.
And there really are two fairly dominant ones, ARM and Intel.
And now RISC-V.
RISC-V is the only global standard.
It is not proprietary.
It does not require license fees.
It does not bring in royalties.
It is free and available for folks to use and have the design freedom that is important to
pushing that leading edge of innovation.
So we are.
We are the definition of open computing.
When you think about the rapid success that we're seeing in our ecosystem today, this is a
testament to the number of stakeholders that we're engaging.
So RISC-V is truly inevitable because of the collective investment of so many around the
world.
This has to do with universities and research institutes, governments and public
institutions that are investing in this.
This has to do with businesses that are investing in this for their local economies.
This has to do with commercial providers, both new startups who are garnering massive amounts of
venture capital funding and other institutional investment, or the types of investments that you're
seeing come into multinationals, multinationals who are looking for design freedom and flexibility
that enables them to add AI, to add acceleration to some of their existing product portfolios.
This is a huge advancement in unleashing the potential of RISC-V.
This also is a different way of designing processors.
So by starting with a base set of instructions, adding only the extensions that you wish to use, you can
achieve new variables for performance, for power, for the specific workloads that you're trying to cater to.
This means that custom processing is far more widely available, and those barriers to entry have come down.
This would be nowhere without our ecosystem.
So software is an absolute essential means to an end.
And the level of software integration and optimization and porting and tooling that we have advancing in RISC-V today is accelerating every day.
We have more tools and resources available within our community and with our partner organizations around the world, such as RISE, with software optimization kits, with several of our vendors here in the booth that are offering new advancements around accelerating that software journey, as well as that design journey.
So what have we accomplished?
We've accomplished a lot.
Over the last two years, we've ratified more than 40 technical specifications that includes 123 ratified extensions.
So this means that you truly take that modular approach.
Small base ISA, pick and choose the extensions that are right for your workload, rather than traditional architecture models where you get an incrementally built ISA, 1,500 extensions or instructions or more.
That is what your base building block is.
Start with something simple and design for your specific workload.
This couldn't be possible without the collaboration of our community.
Collaboration is key.
Each of us bringing the best thought leadership to much of the work that you see going to ratification.
This all then proceeds through a strict governance process with horizontal and vertical committee structure so that we work in harmony.
We work in harmony with one another across these groups.
We're continuing to grow very rapidly.
We have more than 4,300 RISC-V members.
I was just looking at the chart to see if it was updated, because we just got the March numbers in.
We're now more than 4,300 members, 70 different countries.
And for the last five years, I've been telling you, and I'll tell you again, we're evenly distributed around the world.
A third in North America, a third in Europe, and a third in APAC.
This shows you that this is not just a Europe agenda.
This is not just a U.S. agenda or an Asia agenda.
This is a global imperative.
It's very similar to what we saw in open source software.
We are seeing in open hardware.
And RISC-V, as a standard, is the right way to go.
So you see this rapid growth.
We were up near $1 billion.
We were up near $1 billion last year alone.
This is going to market.
You know, many technical projects are interesting.
But they're not meaningful unless you start to see the commercial advancements that go along with that.
And the forecasts for this are very strong.
You see here more than 40% growth and going to 16 billion SOCs by 2030.
know we all walked past that big arm sign on our way into the conference that talked about how many
SOCs they've been shipping. We're not there yet, but we are accelerating rapidly. In fact, there
has not been a faster growing architecture in history, as you see with RISC-V. And that's
because we're in embedded, we're in mobile, we're in automotive, we're in data center, we're in HPC,
we're in hyperscale. We're following all of those threads at the same time. So while our numbers
might not be the same as what you saw in those massive banners on the outside of the conference
hall today, we are rapidly accelerating our growth with our community. So this is our number of SOCs
that are calculated. And we'll get to, well, how does that translate to the money in a minute?
But first, what fields are those in? We're seeing that AI is capitalizing across multiple different
industries. And you see here that, you know, 20, 20 or 20 to 30 percent of all of these major markets
are set to tip over into RISC-V in the coming years. This is huge. Now, remember, just about
four years ago, back in 2020, people had barely heard of RISC-V.
We were still out on road shows educating people on what is RISC-V in the first place.
And now today we're saying we've arrived. Not only have we arrived, but we have this invested,
dedicated community who are continuing to push that leading edge and bringing products to market.
So this is a very exciting time for us. And that money is real. 47 percent CAGR estimated to be,
you know, billions of dollars.
92.7 billion by 2030. This is a massive market. And as you can see on the bottom, it's spanning
industrial, automotive, networking, compute, consumer, and other workloads. So we truly are
seeing all of this progress across the compute spectrum. And so that's a very important takeaway.
Do something because it's cool, but do something for the test of time because it's going to build
your business.
So we're showing a lot of continued growth in IoT as well. And you see, you know, just an example of
where we were in 2018, 2019, 2020, RISC-V not even on the map, right? And as you start to see
the growth in that particular industry, as those new workloads are coming online, that's where that
architecture decision is being made for RISC-V. So you see kind of what the future holds and
where that lies for IoT. This is a rapidly growing domain, and it's anyone's game, and folks are
turning to RISC-V for their strategy. So let's talk a little bit about what some of those
processors are. So you can see here that we've seen a lot of activity from many of the folks in our
community. Codasip and Semidynamic, start-ups like Sci-5 and Ventana, companies around the world.
Even Renesas and Synopsys have been engaging deeply in new RISC-V processors. You see many of these
types of announcements going on at shows like Embedded World. You see new boards coming out and
new things for both the developer community as well as for production. The application space is very
important to us. So you see deep investments and dedication from Qualcomm, Scipia, Scalway, Contar,
and Qataris. Contaris is a very interesting example here in Europe, as a consortium that is dedicated
to looking at automotive in particular, with deep investment from folks like Qualcomm and others.
So have a look at that. Andy's is here in the booth, and they have been dedicated to RISC-V for
several years now and have seen great progress across a huge breadth of applications.
Every time I open up another email from Andy's, it's another domain that they've moved into.
It's a really great progress, and you can see that as a testament to the investment as well as the
dedication of strategic merit. For the development community, bringing Android to RISC-V has unleashed
huge potential. This has been a signal not only to the developer community in porting their applications
to RISC-V, but to the mobile providers as well. So as you see hardware coming online, that software is
ushering in very quickly. By the way, this is a huge signal to our software application community that if
you have not already started planning your journey onto RISC-V, not only are there more tools and resources
to accelerate that journey today, but you're going to be left behind.
If you don't initiate that journey soon. So let's look at some of these industries in particular.
In automotive, nearly 30% of automotive will be RISC-V by 2030. If you're engaged in automotive,
it's not when, you know, what if RISC-V, it's when, and that when is already here.
So think about that across the many domains and areas just within automotive, and this
is something that you'll see is paramount as you look at safety and security and all the other elements that wrap into that.
In data center and cloud, you know, we've heard from some of our stakeholders like Meta and Google and others who have deep
investments in RISC-V and some of the work and some of the challenges that they see and things that we as a community are tackling together. But look not just at primary application workloads, but
also at some of the related things around accelerating a workload or bringing AI onto that existing workload.
That's where many of the initial footprints in data center are today.
Looking more at telecom and consumer devices, 5G has ushered in a completely new era, not just for embedded and others involved here, but in particular for RISC-V. So this, you know, ranges from the
infrastructure behind mobile to the handset itself and bringing all the applications and related functionality within a handset as well. So, you know, it's interesting, the application
processor is only one piece of that phone. Of the dozens of chips within each of your phones, many of those are tipping to RISC-V already. We already talked a little bit about the Internet of Things, but think of this also as
thinking about where does RISC-V fit in the security side of that story and streamlining the, you know, the various attributes that you need within that SOC and enabling that custom processing at a very low power threshold. So some of those low power aspects are things that are easily designed with RISC-V because of the number of variables that you can fine-tune in your design that you simply cannot
do with another architecture.
HPC. You know, HPC is one of the domains that you really truly have a full chip through software stack that is completely open, and that has been great in a lot of our research in academia. You also have the potential, because of reserved encoding space, to add in your custom extensions and proprietary mechanisms to achieve that differentiation that you're looking for.
We have already seen the first RISC-V clusters in competition. They may not have, you know, won the, you know, the golden trophy out the gate, but it is compelling and amazing to see how rapidly RISC-V has made it from embedded to HPC.
I mentioned ecosystem, and this is our landscape. The RISC-V ecosystem is something that, you know, spans from hardware and tool providers and, you know, these logos are going to get smaller and smaller on this chart as we try and get more in. But there is a dynamic version of this online that you can go in and have a look. You know, think about all of the different operating systems and other resources and things that have been used to make this possible.
And here's the operating systems row here. All the different aspects and all the different stakeholders in our ecosystem that need to come together. And by the way, if your logo needs to be on this map, let us know. We'll be sure to bring it on.
So think about how fast you've seen our ecosystem accelerating and what your role is in that community. Think about how are you participating? How are you showing up?
And if you're already a member of RISC-V, it's important to think about that. Because engaging shoulder to shoulder with the engineers and the top minds of this industry who are driving this complete revolution forward is the best way to accelerate your own development within your own companies or the work that you're doing in research or academia.
And that insight back into your company and that allows you to innovate faster. That has business value. It's not just to do something better, faster, more performant, lower power, but it also helps you win in the market. And that's really where research starts to transition into commercialization. And that's what we're seeing in RISC-V.
So for all of these stakeholders, they said, now is the time. Now is the time to push forward.
So for my investment, my resource into RISC-V, and they've started to realize the potential of that.
So thank you. Thank you for joining me today. And hopefully I'll see you in the community. And I invite you to engage there as well. Thank you.