Today represents a first for me.
After a 25 year career, this is the first time I've ever worn a sports jacket in a professional
setting.
How does it look?
I bought this thing on Friday, and when you buy a sports coat from the store, you know,
they sell these things to anybody, they're not made for you.
The sleeves came all the way down to my knuckles.
And my wife, realizing that I was not going to have enough time to get it tailored, she's
like, "It looks fine."
And I'm standing in the mirror, feeling like I was a seven year old wearing his father's
jacket.
And I got desperate.
On Sunday, I'm Googling for someone that can do alterations, and all I see is closed, closed,
opens on Tuesday.
And I'm like, "I don't have a chance."
And about 15 miles away from my home, there was a person that was open till 9:00.
And I'm a little worried that, why are you open till 9:00 on a Sunday?
Aren't you busy all week that you need time off?
There's a reason why he's open when no one else is.
But I had to take my chances.
So I get in my car.
Before getting in our car, I did call.
And I said, "Hey, how much?"
"And how long to tailor a men's suit, sports coat?"
He was like, "A week."
And I was like, "I need it much sooner than that."
He said, "Two days."
And I said, "You're getting close."
"I need it today."
He was like, "Ah, you got to pick it up by 4:00."
So I drove down there, and he told me $20.
I'm really getting nervous now.
And I pull up, and it's a house in a normal neighborhood.
No storefront, no fancy signage.
And he opened the door with no shoes on.
And I'm thinking to myself, I'm not getting this suit back if I leave it here.
But you only live once.
So I walk in, and I saw the sewing machines in the corner.
So I'm like, all right, it's getting a little legit.
I see other garments waiting to be tailored.
Maybe I am in the right place.
And he hung it up.
on a string hanging from the ceiling. And it twirled around. I'm like, what are you doing?
And he asked me to put the jacket on. And I was like, what do you think? He was like, yeah,
you definitely need to take it down an inch or so. And so I leave the jacket with him.
And I come back. And I put the jacket on. And here's the thing. The name of this place is
Bethany and Linda's Alterations. That's his American name. He didn't speak English that well.
And he did his best to make me feel comfortable. I put the jacket on. And that's when I learned
that language is universal. Watch how I use it. Silence and a smile is the same in every language.
And I put this jacket on. And it reminded me something.
We live in a fairly open society.
We live in a society where I can buy a jacket that wasn't quite made for me.
And he possessed the skill through open knowledge to tailor it for my exact needs.
In the software world, we call this patches or features or bug fixes. But he made it perfect
just for me. And I smiled. And I gave him $60. And he was so happy. The first thing he said,
this is too much money. It's only $20. I said, you can keep it. The jacket's perfect.
And he smiled like a child. And he held the $60 close to his chest. He said, I'm taking the family
out to dinner tonight.
And the world is filled of these hidden maintainers. No one really knows their names.
They don't work for a big, fancy company. But they do their best to make sure that we
get to use the things that work for us.
All those bug fixes, all those GitHub issues, there's a silent league of maintainers out here
doing that kind of work, tailor-fitting our software for our own needs.
When we think about what it takes to deliver on some of this software, I think we're in this
really pivotal point. Because open source has been such this powerful thing that we sometimes,
I think, take it for granted. It's tricky. I want you to go through a thought experiment.
Imagine if you had a thought experiment. And you had a thought experiment. And you had a thought
experiment. And you had a thought experiment. And you had a thought experiment. And you had
been diagnosed with an untreatable disease. Not even curable, untreatable. And so you decide to
dedicate your entire life work to this disease. And the good news is you don't have to start from
scratch. You get to rely on previous science. You get to use very mature machines, microscopes.
You get to read all the research papers that came before you. And then you find a solution.
you've done it you can finally save yourself you have to make a pivotal decision do you keep this
formula for yourself or do you decide to share with other people that there is no right answer
here because why not capitalize on all the value that you've just now introduced to the world
isn't it only fair that you get to capitalize from this i'm pretty sure some of you in the
audience would be like who in their right mind would miss out on an opportunity to make billions
of dollars from their own invention well if you look around the room here today those people are
sitting next to you think about some of these global projects that we have that the very same
maintainers could have easily chosen to start a company and go to proprietary route and keep it
all for themselves but instead they chose to open source
and stand behind those projects and make it available to all it's a very tricky place to be
and i don't think there's a perfect answer for this so i have a lot of empathy with companies
contributors and maintainers that are struggling with how long can i do this for we hear about
open source sustainability but i'm not quite sure people understand what this means
i've been an open source contributor for a while and there's this saying if you're the
smartest person in the room then you're in the wrong room and you should leave
but eventually if we all did that then the room would be empty and when i got into open source
those smart people didn't leave the room they chose to collaborate instead they even made a
seat for me i sat down didn't know what i was doing didn't know how to contribute didn't know
the workflow process but they figured out a way to make it so the documentation the code reviews
this is what happens
when the smart people stay in the room
so one day i got to return the favor i remember i open sourced my first project CompD
wasn't super popular but it did make its way around the world i remember going to an open source conference in europe conference called FOSDEM
and i'm standing in the back of this room and there is someone that i don't know that was given a presentation about CompD
they had all these wonderful things to say i'm in the back just smiling my ass off
i'm not quite famous but people know who i am or at least they're aware of the work that i do
and they went on to tell the audience of how it was so important that i chose not only to scratch
my own itch but i also helped them with theirs i felt really good about that project and so as a
maintainer i went home and said let me add more features let me fix a few bugs i'm now more motivated
than ever you got to be careful when you're a maintainer motivated to that degree because you
can hide burnout underneath the cloth of success it's really easy to do and i remember there was a
time when i said no for the first time see what CompD does it takes data from key value stores
like etcd a database and there was a new company on the scene they've been around for a while
called hashicorp i had been a contributor to hashicorp and they've contributed to my project
CompD what's supposed to happen and one day they introduced a new product called volt and i said hey
i have no interest as a maintainer integrating with that product but for them this is a very
important product and they would like CompD to support it because at this point CompD had become
somewhat popular and they were recommending it to their community but here i was saying no
so when you say no as a maintainer something has to give
how do we resolve issues when there's a conflict or a difference of opinion
well in this scenario they chose to make another project a clone of mine if you're a maintainer
you realize that at the top of that github repository there's the fork button anyone
can click it and settle disputes without any arguments i woke up one day and they had a new
project called console template and they posted it and it was at the top of hacker news and i'm
sitting there smiling but the internet can't see that so in my defense
this thing rises to the top spot on hacker news how dare big evil hashi corp
take kelsey's work and rebrand it as their own
they should have just contributed back there was no need for a competing project
and i'm reading this as like oh they don't understand what has happened
when you get to the point where you can influence someone else to produce something
else this is also an achievement and so i replied this is open source this is what's supposed to
happen do you think that i did all of this work by myself there were some of the largest contributors
i didn't invent the programming language that comp d is written in i didn't invent
the operating system that comp d is written in if you zoom out we've been in this together this whole
time
and so i applaud the efforts for this new project to exist and i'm quite flattered that this larger
company decided to take inspiration from me and i will go on to speak at a number of their conferences
because that's what good community members do even when we compete we still find rooms to collaborate
and i remember one time i was collaborating with that particular company hashi corp and i'm doing
this keynote and they gave me one of their hashi corp shirts my last name is hightower and their
logo has this wonderful h and i put it on says the h stands for hightower now we're proudly on that
keynote stage and i remember having this shirt on after the final keynote that i gave they did
a company-wide picture at this point hashi corp grows to about i don't know three to four hundred
people and they all line up on the stage and we take photos and they're like one of the founders
mitchell hashimoto kelsey get in the front row kelsey get in the front row kelsey get in the front
row you're in the photo you're like family so i get into the photo and i stand there and i pose
with my h on and i straighten it out just so it looks perfect and we take the photo and i was like
mitchell this is our chance to do the funniest thing ever it's like what do you have in mind
and he posts the photo on twitter and as the ceo and founder of hashi corp
he wrote i'm so happy that kelsey is joining hashi corp
now as an executive myself at google this is really interesting
and i let it bake for hours the hr department is like what's going on when did kelsey leave
when you work with almost 200 000 people no one knows what's going on
so people were emailing me like congratulations i think
and you just
start typing but never send anything so she says dot dot dot
so after a couple of hours because it started getting really serious
you know it's serious when your vp puts a meeting on your calendar to discuss things
so i declined the meeting is like it's a joke and i responded but hashi corp is like family
and i remember during that time i had this phrase different company same team
that's how i've always thought about this open source collaboration and i've contributed to
many of the hashi core projects and the reason why i'm bringing up hashi corp in particular because
i have a lot of empathy for my family and what they go through i also advise lots of startups
and they all have this sentiment that seems to be pretty new from the outsider's view the early days
of open source seem to try to make better versions of things that existed already some of the earlier
operating systems corn shell tobacco and other things i've always thought about this open source
was a blueprint and a template and the goal was to turn proprietary software and make it open and of
course they got better over time to the point where they became industry standards but imagine
trying to build a company in this error this is an extreme amount of challenge if you're a small
company or startup how do you sell something that you give away completely for free i don't have a
perfect answer for that i don't think the answer is changing your license that's not going to work
folks you're going to have to do something better than that you're going to have to do something
just like my taylor did you're going to have to figure out how to offer value in an open ecosystem
because if you don't someone else will figure out a way to do it instead the question i'd like
to leave with all the founders and customers out there that are struggling with this
we have to ask ourselves what is the moat that they need to build and my response to that is why
are you trying to build a moat in the age of flight that is not a sustainable path we're going to have
to figure out how to collaborate on equal terms now a lot of you are going to go out and enjoy
the next two days of this conference and i want to leave you with one more phrase when you're
thinking about whether you should contribute or not whether you should try that new idea and make
it open you're going to have to figure out how to collaborate on equal terms now a lot of you are going to go out and enjoy the next two days of this conference and i want to leave you with one more phrase when you're thinking about whether you should contribute or not whether you should try that new idea and make it open
one phrase that i always return to in moments like this is there are some people that have ideas
and there are some ideas that have people and don't forget that last part thank you