One little bit of news that recently dropped. There was an announcement that
in China the state organizations are going to be adopting RISC-V or at least
exploring it. Tell us a little bit about that. Well I can't speak to other
governments but you know we are seeing exponential growth of RISC-V around
the world. Last year we saw more than 25% growth year-over-year in our
membership. We're more than 4,300 members now which is probably even up a little
from our press release because we got last month's close. But we're seeing this
diversity of interest in RISC-V that's really profound. We've got about a
third of our members in North America, Europe, and APAC. Pretty evenly
distributed. And the really cool thing is I've been
saying that for five years. It hasn't changed. The level of interest is
continuing to skyrocket evenly and profoundly around the world and we're
adding into that new areas. So the Ministry of Brazil has just signed
agreements with the European Union and with you know working out things with
Spain and Portugal to do even more for Latin America and Spanish-speaking countries. So
the Ministry of Brazil has joined RISC-V and sit on our board now and that's
great because when it comes to you know kind of that government support, that
federal support of RISC-V, it's really important. And whether I'm talking to the
European Union on the funds and grants that are going on for RISC-V or
countries like Brazil or India that are investing in RISC-V, the main thing here
is invest local. Shore up that local economy. Engage in the digital economy.
Teach computer science in all your universities and do it on RISC-V.
Yeah. Rather than those other architectures. And what you're going to do
is engage that in the global economy. Don't do it for yourself. Do it in a
global way and that's why RISC-V as a standard is so important. Okay I've been
talking a lot. Your turn. Well look I look forward with this news about Brazil I
look forward to the RISC-V Carnival standard. That should be fun. What do you
what are some of the industries that are driving all of this growth? I mean I know
that we've been talking a lot about automotive which is exciting and cool
but what are some of your other favorites? So yes, industries driving like
automotive. I didn't miss that. You know so embedded this is kind of where it
started for RISC-V and we've started to really move up the compute spectrum into
even more robust or performant workloads. So embedded is all about lightweight, low
power, portable, very you know single focus design and that has been an
incredible start and we're starting to see that grow into mobile. We've seen a
lot with Android coming onto the systems for or onto RISC-V for application
processing but that's not the only processor in your phone. You also have
Wi-Fi, Bluetooth, all the other pieces and parts of your phone that you know
there's a lot of area there that everyone can take advantage of. You move
from there into you know tablets, laptops, we've got a couple of those here at the
show. You move from there into data center and the workloads that are
looking to come on to RISC-V and the data center is already pretty profound.
You look at and hear from companies who have massive data center footprints, meta,
talks a lot about RISC-V. Yeah. You hear from you know other hyperscalers
that have incorporated RISC-V into their designs. This is where innovation comes
together with volume and it's RISC-V at scale. So RISC-V is hockey sticking it
seems like and another a whole industry that's been threatening to do that for a
long time and is near and dear to my heart is IOT. So they're obviously very
interested in low power, edge devices, that kind of thing. Are you seeing those
companies in those spaces getting on board with with RISC-V too? So RISC-V is
sort of a catalyst at the right time right place for things like AI and
acceleration and chip and everything. Somebody earlier today was saying
there's gonna be a chip on every cucumber in the supermarket and I was
like whoa. Delicious. Yes, right. Goes well on a salad. So yeah you do have that profound
opportunity but before RISC-V you had a very few people or companies who
could engage in that opportunity because there were too many barriers to entry.
RISC-V that's you know anyone can do with what
they wish so that's why you have more design houses on RISC-V now than any
other architecture in history. So let's get evangelical here. Ladies and
gentlemen, boys and girls, we're gonna get evangelical. Nobody gets that because
we're all in Germany but that's fine. Let's talk about open source because
look RISC-V is embedded in open source and and is clearly a driving force there. I
think that open, personally I think open source is critical to success and
embedded in almost every computing space and there's a place for the walled garden
there's a place for proprietary but I think open source is where a lot of
innovation happens and I know that the RISC-V is really supporting a lot of
that innovation so I want to hear about some of the the open source projects
that you're excited about that you've been seeing happen. So I think open source
is a great idea. I love open source, near and dear to my heart but let's not get too
confused. RISC-V is not open source. RISC-V is a standard and the
difference here is that you take a standard and you freeze it for the test
of time right because if you decide to go off and do your own special Bluetooth
or your own special you know name your favorite hardware interconnect standard
yeah you're all by yourself.
You don't want to be off in those weeds. So a global standard is something
that you collaborate on in our case openly collaborate on and then freeze it
for the test of time and that's a really cool thing yeah and it takes time and it
takes diligence and it takes a lot of like interpersonal like dialogue with
one another in the community that we all come to agree on things right and that's
hard work and we're doing that hard work. We support then open collaborative
collaboration in open source software where you can apply patches. You can
invent something over the weekend and put it up into a repo right yeah and so
yes we absolutely support and honor the open source software community as well.
In fact getting all of those distros to run on RISC-V, getting all the
applications to say you know what I run on these architectures I need to run on
RISC-V too because that's my opportunity. It's not because it's technically
cool it's because there's business value and so what we've seen for you know
Android is an example for the Android team to support RISC-V we needed to
first see volumes and enough customer demand to warrant that investment from
the team. So those are the types of like next era that we're ushering in both in
standards as well as an open source. So as a reporter I wouldn't be doing my
job if I didn't ask the hard questions. So I got I got to put you on the spot
here. Where does RISC-V need to move to that you aren't in yet? That you
aren't that you haven't started exploring yet?
RISC-V has already made like inches forward across the full compute domain. What we
have yet to do is get to scale across all of those domains. So we are on the precipice of
you know going into data center in laptops and all the other devices. There
are lots of predictions about RISC-V in HPC, RISC-V in cell phones and when it
will be the primary processor when it will be all of the processors. A few
years ago I was talking to an analyst who said you know more than 25% of all design
starts include at least one RISC-V core. That was a few years ago. Last summer I talked
to him and I said so what's the number now? And he told me you know it's hard to
find a design start that does not include at least one RISC-V core. So we
are arriving at that design phase and you're going to see us move very
rapidly across that spectrum in the next few years.
So if I don't ask this next question the secret cabal of tech journalists has to
come and take me away. Let's talk about AI.
I know RISC-V is heavily involved in a lot of AI projects and I've talked to
several companies here today that are that are leveraging RISC-V in their AI.
What parts of the RISC-V standard are ideally suited into into working with AI
and why is that so attractive. So AI as well as any other processing has to do
with how much design flexibility you can bring to that work
load and that's where RISC-V and it's you know complete menu of different open
extensions comes into play. But where folks can really find their competitive
edge is in some of the reserved encoding space that you can use for your own
proprietary extensions, your own proprietary or your secret sauce that
makes your AI better than someone else's. But there are things that we're doing as
base building blocks like our vector and vector crypto and other pieces that we've been
ratifying that allow for that new era of design freedom.
So as we get near the end of our time here I like my favorite question to ask is the
one I saved for last and no this is great because it makes you do all the work and the
question is what didn't I think to ask you that's really contributing to the growth of
RISC-V and the strength and everything that everybody should be knowing about but they're
not talking about enough yet.
So I think it's the strength of what you truly get from a collaborative community like this is that you're able to
progress not only our shared mission but you're able to say like wow look
there's you know six other people doing something I thought I had to go do by
myself let's do that together bang it out and then go do the next cool
interesting thing together. You don't have collaboration at scale if you're
working in a proprietary environment. In a proprietary
environment that's called development partner. That's a one to one relationship.
When you have a one to many relationship you actually reduce the level of risk
that's in your business and technical strategy for taking a particular
direction. So that collaboration and that contribution and developer might and
strength is something I think is often assumed and overlooked in a community
like ours. It accelerates your individual traction as well as brings learning back into
your organization that you wouldn't get any other way.
Well folks I think the message here is pretty clear. It's time to take a risk.
Five.
Thank you.